Ms Dufresne, describe
the confrontation you had with your wife the night she was murdered.
It was very bitter.
She said she was glad I knew, that she hated all the sneaking around.
And she said that she wanted a divorce in Reno.
What was your response
I told her I would not grant one
I'll see you in hell before I see you in Reno.
Those were your words, according to your neighbors.
If they say so.
I really don't remember
I was upset.
What happened after you argued with your wife
She packed a bag.
She packed a bag to go and stay with Ms Quentin.
Glenn Quentin, golf pro at the Snowden Hills Country Club
whom you had discovered was your wife's lover.
Did you follow her
I went to a few bars first.
Later, I drove to his house to confront them
They weren't home.
I parked in the turnout
and waited.
With what intention
I'm not sure.
I was confused..
drunk.
I think..
mostly I wanted to scare them.
When they arrived, you went up to the house and murdered them.
No, I was sobering up.
I got back in the car and I drove home to sleep it off.
Along the way, I threw my gun into the Royal River.
I've been very clear on this point.
I get hazy where the cleaning woman shows up the following morning
and finds your wife in bed with her lover
riddled with .38 caliber bullets.
Does that strike you as a fantastic coincidence, or is it just me
Yes, it does.
Yet you still maintain you threw your gun into the river
before the murders took place.
That's very convenient.
It's the truth.
The police dragged that river for three days, and nary a gun was found
so no comparison could be made between your gun and the bullets
taken from the bloodstained corpses of the victims.
And that also
is very convenient
Isn't it, Ms Dufresne
Since I am innocent of this crime
I find it decidedly inconvenient that the gun was never found.
Ladies and gentlemen, you've heard all the evidence.
We have the accused at the scene of the crime
We have footprints.
Bullets on the ground bearing his fingerprints.
A broken bourbon bottle, likewise with fingerprints.
And most of all
we have a beautiful young woman and her lover
lying dead in each other's arms.
They had sinned.
But was their crime so great
as to merit a death sentence
While you think about that..
think about this:
A revolver holds six bullets, not eight.
I submit that this was not a hot blooded crime of passion.
That at least could be understood, if not condoned.
No.
This was revenge..
of a much more brutal, cold blooded nature
Consider this:
Four bullets per victim.
Not six shots fired, but eight.
That means that he fired the gun empty
and then stopped to reload
so that he could shoot each of them again.
An extra bullet per lover
right in the head.
You strike me as a particularly icy and remorseless man, Ms Dufresne.
It chills my blood just to look at you.
By the power vested in me by the state of Maine
I hereby order you to serve two life sentences back to back
one for each of your victims
So be it
Sit.
We see you've served 20 years of a life sentence
Yes, sir
You feel you've been rehabilitated
Absolutely, sir.
I mean, I learned my lesson.
I can honestly say that I'm a changed man.
I'm no longer a danger to society.
That's God's honest truth.
Hey, Red.
How'd it go
Same old shit, different day.
Yeah, I know how you feel.
I'm up for rejection next week.
Yeah, I got rejected last week.
It happens.
Hey, Red, bump me a deck.
Get out of my face, man
You're into me for five packs already.
Four
Five
There must be a con like me in every prison in America.
I'm the guy who can get it for you.
Cigarettes, a bag of reefer, if that's your thing
a bottle of brandy to celebrate your kid's high school graduation.
Damn near anything within reason.
Yes, sir
I'm a regular Sears and Roebuck.
So when Andy Dufresne came to me in 1949
and asked me to smuggle Rita Hayworth into the prison for him..
I told him, No problem.
Officers to main gate
Officers to main gate.
Secure main gate.
Andy came to Shawshank Prison
in early 1947 for murdering his wife and the fella she was banging.
On the outside, he'd been vice president of a large Portland bank.
Good work for a man so young.
Hey, Red.
You speak English, butt steak
You follow this officer.
I never seen such a sorry looking heap of maggot shit in all my life.
Hey, fish
Come over here
Taking bets today, Red
Smokes or coin
Bettor's choice.
Smokes
Put me down for two.
All right, who's your horse
That little sack of shit.
Eighth
He'll be first
Bullshit
I'll take that action.
You're out some smokes, son.
If you're so smart, you call it.
I'll take the chubby fat ass there.
The fifth one
Put me down for a quarter deck.
Fresh fish today
We're reeling them in
I admit I didn't think much of Andy first time I laid eyes on him.
Looked like a stiff breeze would blow him over.
That was my first impression of the man.
What do you say
That tall drink of water with the silver spoon up his ass.
That guy
Never happen.
Ten cigarettes
That's a rich bet.
Who's going to prove me wrong
Heywood
Jigger
Skeets
Floyd
Four brave souls.
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
All prisoners, return to your cellblocks.
Turn to the right
Eyes front.
This is Ms Hadley
He's captain of the guards.
I'm Ms Norton, the warden.
You are convicted felons.
That's why they've sent you to me
Rule number one:
No blasphemy.
I'll not have the Lord's name taken in vain in my prison.
The other rules
you'll figure out as you go along
Any questions
When do we eat
You eat when we say you eat.
You shit when we say you shit, and piss when we say you piss.
You got that, you maggot dick motherfucker
On your feet
I believe in two things:
Discipline and the Bible.
Here, you'll receive both.
Put your trust in the Lord.
Your ass belongs to me.
Welcome to Shawshank.
Unhook them.
Turn around.
That's enough.
Move to the end of the cage.
Turn around
Delouse him.
Turn around.
Move out of the cage
Pick up your clothes and Bible.
Next man up
To the right
Right
Right.
Left.
The first night's the toughest
No doubt about it.
They march you in naked as the day you were born
skin burning and half blind from that delousing shit.
And when they put you in that cell
and those bars slam home
that's when you know it's for real.
Old life blown away in the blink of an eye.
Nothing left but all the time in the world to think about it.
Most new fish come close to madness the first night.
Somebody always breaks down crying.
Happens every time.
The only question is
who's it going to be
It's as good a thing to bet on as any, I guess.
I had my money on Andy Dufresne.
Lights out
I remember my first night.
Seems like a long time ago.
Hey, fish.
Fish, fish.
What are you, scared of the dark
Bet you wish your daddy never dicked your mama
Piggy
Pork
I want me a pork chop.
Poke your ass out, give me a first look
Keep it down.
The boys always go fishing with first timers.
And they don't quit till they reel someone in.
Hey, Fat Ass.
Fat Ass
Talk to me, boy.
I know you're there
I can hear you breathing.
Don't you listen to these nitwits, you hear me
This place ain't so bad.
Tell you what
I'll introduce you around, make you feel right at home.
I know a couple of big old bull queers that'd just
love to make your acquaintance.
Especially that big, white, mushy butt of yours.
God
I don't belong here
We have a winner
I want to go home
And it's Fat Ass by a nose
Fresh fish
I don't belong here.
I want to go home
I want my mother
I had your mother
She wasn't that great
What the Christ is this horseshit
He blasphemed
I'll tell the warden.
You'll tell him with my baton up your ass
You gotta let me out
What is your malfunction, you fat barrel of monkey spunk
Please
I ain't supposed to be here.
Not me
I won't count to three
Not even to one.
You shut up, or I'll sing you a lullaby
Shut up, man
Shut up
There's been a mistake.
You don't understand
I'm not supposed to be here.
Open that cell.
Me neither
They run this place like a fucking prison
Son of a bitch
Captain, take it easy
If I hear so much as a mouse fart in here tonight
I swear by God and Jesus, you will all visit the infirmary.
Every last motherfucker in here.
Call the trustees
Take that tub of shit down to the infirmary.
His first night in the joint, Dufresne cost me two packs of cigarettes.
He never made a sound.
Tier 3 north, clear count
Tier 2 north, clear
Tier 2 south, clear.
Tier 3 south, clear.
Tier 1 south, clear
Tier 4 south, clear.
Prepare to roll out.
Roll out
Are you going to eat that
I hadn't planned on it.
Do you mind
That's nice and ripe.
Jake says thank you.
Fell out of his nest over by the plate shop.
I'm going to look after him until he's big enough to fly.
Oh, no
Here he comes.
Morning, fellas.
Fine morning, isn't it
You know why it's a fine morning, don't you
Send them down
I want them lined up
just like a pretty little chorus line.
Look at that.
I can't stand this guy
Oh, Lord
Yes
Richmond, Virginia.
Smell my ass
After he smells mine.
That's a shame about your horse coming in last and all.
But I sure do love that winning horse of mine, though.
I owe that boy a big kiss when I see him.
Why don't you give him some of your cigarettes instead
Lucky fuck
Hey, Tyrell.
You pull infirmary duty this week
How's my horse doing anyway
Dead.
Hadley busted his head up pretty good.
Doc had gone home for the night.
Poor bastard lay there till this morning.
By then, there wasn't nothing we could do.
What was his name
What'd you say
I was just wondering if anyone knew his name.
What the fuck do you care, new fish
Doesn't fucking matter what his name was
He's dead.
Anybody come at you yet
Anybody get to you yet
Hey, we all need friends in here.
I could be a friend to you.
Hard to get.
I like that.
Andy kept pretty much to himself at first.
I guess he had a lot on his mind
trying to adapt to life on the inside.
Wasn't until a month went by before he opened his mouth
to say more than two words to somebody.
As it turned out
that somebody was me.
I'm Andy Dufresne.
Wife killing banker.
Why'd you do it
I didn't, since you ask.
You're going to fit right in.
Everybody in here's innocent
Didn't you know that
What you in here for
Didn't do it
Lawyer fucked me.
Rumor has it you're a real cold fish.
You think your shit smells sweeter than most
Is that right
What do you think
To tell you the truth, I haven't made up my mind.
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time.
I wonder if you might get me a rock hammer.
A rock hammer.
What is it and why
What do you care
For a toothbrush, I wouldn't ask
I'd quote a price.
But a toothbrush is a non lethal object, isn't it
Fair enough.
A rock hammer is about six or seven inches long.
Looks like a miniature pickax
Pickax
For rocks.
Quartz
And some mica, shale
limestone.
So
So I'm a rock hound.
At least I was in my old life
I'd like to be again.
Or maybe you'd like to sink your toy into somebody's skull.
No, I have no enemies here.
No
Wait a while.
Word gets around.
The Sisters have taken quite a liking to you.
Especially Bogs.
Don't suppose it would help if I told them I'm not homosexual.
Neither are they.
You have to be human first
They don't qualify.
Bull queers take by force
That's all they want or understand.
If I were you, I'd grow eyes in the back of my head.
Thanks for the advice
Well, that's free.
You understand my concern.
If there's trouble, I won't use the rock hammer.
Then I'd guess you want to escape
Tunnel under the wall, maybe.
What did I miss
What's so funny
You'll understand when you see the rock hammer.
What's an item like this usually go for
Seven dollars in any rock and gem shop.
My normal markup's 20 percent.
But this is a specialty item.
Risk goes up, price goes up
Let's make it an even 10 bucks.
Ten it is.
Waste of money, if you ask me.
Why's that
Folks around this joint love surprise inspections.
They find it, you're going to lose it.
If they catch you, you don't know me.
Mention my name, we never do business again.
Not for shoelaces or a stick of gum
Now you got that
I understand.
Thank you, Ms.
Red.
Name's Red.
Why do they call you that
Maybe it's because I'm lrish.
I could see why some of the boys took him for snobby.
He had a quiet way about him
a walk and a talk that just wasn't normal around here.
He strolled
like a man in the park without a care or a worry in the world.
Like he had on an invisible coat that would shield him from this place.
I think it would be fair to say
I liked Andy from the start.
Let's go
Some of us got a schedule to keep.
Move it
Come on, move it
How you doing
How's the wife treating you
Keep it moving.
Red.
Andy was right.
I finally got the joke.
It would take a man about 600 years
to tunnel under the wall with one of these.
Book
Not today.
No.
Delivery for Dufresne.
Book
Dufresne, here's your book.
Thanks.
We're running low on hexite
Get on back and fetch us up some.
This will blind you.
Honey, hush.
That's it
You fight
Better that way.
I wish I could tell you Andy fought the good fight
and the Sisters let him be.
I wish I could tell you that
but prison is no fairy tale world.
He never said who did it.
But we all knew.
Things went on like that for a while.
Prison life consists of routine
and then more routine.
Every so often, Andy would show up with fresh bruises.
The Sisters kept at him.
Sometimes he was able to fight them off.
Sometimes not.
And that's how it went for Andy.
That was his routine.
I do believe those first two years were the worst for him.
And I also believe if things had gone on that way
this place would have got the best of him.
But then, in the spring of 1949..
the powers that be decided:
The roof of the license plate factory needs resurfacing.
I need a dozen volunteers for a week's work.
As you know
special detail carries with it special privileges.
It was outdoor detail
and May is one damned fine month to be working outdoors.
Stay in line there.
More than 100 men volunteered for the job.
Wallace E
Unger.
Ellis Redding.
Wouldn't you know it
Me and some fellows I know were among the names called.
Andrew Dufresne.
It only cost us a pack of smokes per man.
I made my usual 20 percent, of course.
So this big shot lawyer calls me long distance from Texas
I say, Yeah
He says, Sorry to inform you, but your brother just died.
I'm sorry to hear that
I'm not
He was an asshole.
Ran off years ago
Figured him for dead
So this lawyer fellow says to me:
He died a rich man. Oil wells and shit
Close to a million bucks.
A million bucks
Incredible how lucky some assholes get
You going to see any of that
Thirty five thousand
That's what he left me.
Dollars
Yep.
That's great
That's like winning the sweepstakes.
Isn't it
Dumb shit, what do you think the government will do to me
Take a big wet bite out of my ass is what.
Poor Byron.
Terrible fucking luck, huh
Crying shame.
Some people really got it awful.
Andy, are you nuts
Keep your eyes on your mop, man
You'll pay some tax, but you'll still end up
Yeah, maybe enough to buy a new car, and then what
I got to pay tax on the car
Repair
maintenance, kids pestering you to take them for a ride all the time.
Then if you figure your tax wrong, you pay out of your own pocket.
I tell you
Uncle Sam
He puts his hand in your shirt and squeezes your tit till it's purple.
Getting himself killed
Keep tarring.
Some brother
Shit
Ms Hadley
do you trust your wife
Oh, that's funny.
You'll look funnier sucking my dick with no teeth.
What I mean is, do you think she'd go behind your back
Step aside, Mert
This fucker's having himself an accident.
He'll push him off
If you trust her, you can keep
that 35,000.
What did you say
Thirty five thousand.
All of it.
Every penny
You better start making sense.
If you want to keep it, give it to your wife.
The IRS allows a one time only gift to your spouse for up to $60,000.
Bullshit
Tax free
Tax free.
IRS can't touch one cent.
You're that smart banker what killed his wife.
Why should I believe you
So I can end up in here with you
It's legal
Ask the IRS
They'll say the same thing.
I feel stupid telling you this
I'm sure you would have investigated.
I don't need you to tell me where the bear shit in the buckwheat.
Of course not
But you do need someone to set it up for you.
That'll cost you
A lawyer.
A bunch of ball washing bastards
I suppose I could set it up for you
That would save you some money.
You get the forms, I'll prepare them
nearly free of charge.
I'd only ask three beers apiece for each of my coworkers.
Coworkers. That's rich
A man working outdoors feels more like a man
if he can have a bottle of suds
That's only my opinion
sir.
What are you jimmies staring at
Let's go
Work
And that's how it came to pass
that on the second to last day of the job
the convict crew that tarred the factory roof in the spring of '49
wound up sitting in a row at 10:00 in the morning
drinking icy cold beer, courtesy of the hardest screw
that ever walked a turn at Shawshank State Prison.
Drink up while it's cold, ladies.
The colossal prick even managed to sound magnanimous.
We sat and drank with the sun on our shoulders and felt like free men.
We could have been tarring the roof of one of our own houses.
We were the lords of all creation.
As for Andy
he spent that break hunkered in the shade
a strange little smile on his face
watching us drink his beer.
Want a cold one
No, thanks
I gave up drinking.
You could argue he'd done it to curry favor with the guards.
Or maybe make a few friends among us cons.
Me
I think he did it just to feel normal again
if only for a short while.
King me.
Chess
Now there's a game of kings
What
Civilized
Strategic.
And a total fucking mystery
I hate it.
Let me teach you someday.
Sure.
We could get a board together.
You're talking to the right man
I can get things, right
We might do business on a board, and I'll carve the pieces myself.
One side in alabaster, one in soapstone
What do you think
I think it'll take years.
Years I got
What I don't have are the rocks.
Pickings are pretty slim in the yard.
Pebbles, mostly.
We're getting to be kind of friends, aren't we
Yeah, I guess.
Can I ask you something
Why'd you do it
I'm innocent, Red.
Just like everybody else here.
What are you in for
Murder
Same as you.
Innocent
Only guilty man in Shawshank.
Where's the canary
How did you know
How did I know what
So you don't know.
Come.
This is where the canary is.
Quite a surprise to hear a woman singing in my house, eh
That's quite a
surprise.
Wait, wait.
Here she comes.
I like this part when she does that shit with her hair.
I know
I've seen it three times this month.
Gilda, are you decent
Me
God, I love it.
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time
What do you want
Rita Hayworth
What
Can you get her
So this is Johnny Farrel
I've heard a lot about you.
Take a few weeks
Weeks
I don't have her stuffed down the front of my pants right now, sorry to say.
But I'll get her.
Relax.
Thanks.
Take a walk
I got to change reels
I said fuck off
Ain't you going to scream
Let's get this over with.
He broke my fucking nose
Now
I'm going to open my fly
and you'll swallow what I give you to swallow.
Then you'll swallow Rooster's
You broke his nose.
He ought to have something to show for it.
You put it in my mouth, you lose it.
No, you don't understand.
Do that and I'll put all eight inches of this in your ear.
All right, but you should know that sudden, serious brain injury
causes the victim to bite down hard.
In fact, I hear the bite reflex is so strong
they have to pry the victim's jaws open
with a crowbar.
Where do you get this shit
I read it.
You know how to read, you ignorant fuck
Honey.
You shouldn't
Bogs didn't put anything in Andy's mouth.
And neither did his friends.
What they did do is beat him within an inch of his life.
Andy spent a month in the infirmary.
Bogs spent a week in the hole.
Time's up, Bogs.
It's your world, boss.
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
All prisoners report for lockdown.
What
Where's he going
Grab his ankles.
No
Help me
Two things never happened again after that.
The Sisters never laid a finger on Andy again.
And Bogs never walked again.
They transferred him to a minimum security hospital upstate.
To my knowledge, he lived out the rest of his days
drinking his food through a straw.
Andy could use a nice welcome back when he gets out of the infirmary.
Sounds good to us.
I figure we owe him that much for the beer.
The man likes to play chess.
Let's get him some rocks.
Guys
I got one.
I got one
Look
Heywood, that isn't soapstone
And it ain't alabaster either.
What are you, a fucking geologist
He's right
It ain't.
What the hell is it then
It's a horse apple.
Bullshit
No, horseshit.
Petrified.
Oh, Jesus.
Damn
Despite a few hitches, the boys came through in fine style.
And by the weekend he was due back
we had enough rocks saved up to keep him busy till rapture.
Also got a big shipment in that week.
Cigarettes..
chewing gum
sipping whisky
playing cards with naked ladies on them
You name it
And, of course, the most important item:
Rita Hayworth herself.
Okay, look alive
Open all tiers.
Heads up
They're tossing cells.
They're tossing cells
119.
123.
On your feet.
Face the wall.
Turn around and face the warden.
Pleased to see you reading this.
Any favorite passages
Watch ye, therefore, for ye know not..
when the master of the house cometh.
Mark 13:35.
I've always liked that one
But I prefer:
I am the light of the world
Ye that followeth me shall have the light of life.
John, chapter 8, verse 12.
I hear you're good with numbers.
How nice.
Man should have a skill.
Explain this.
It's called a rock blanket
For shaping and polishing rocks.
A little hobby of mine.
It's pretty clean.
Some contraband here, but nothing to get in a twist over.
I can't say I approve of this.
But I suppose
exceptions can be made.
Lock them up
I almost forgot.
I'd hate to deprive you of this.
Salvation lies within.
Yes, sir.
Tossing cells was just an excuse.
Truth is..
Norton wanted to size Andy up.
My wife made that in church group.
Very nice, sir.
You enjoy working the laundry
No, sir
Not especially.
Perhaps we can find something more
befitting a man of your education.
Hey, Jake
Where's Brooks
I thought I heard you out here.
I've been reassigned to you.
I know, they told me.
Ain't that a kick in the head
Well, I'll give you the dime tour.
Come on.
Well, here she is.
The Shawshank Prison Library.
National Geographics
Reader's Digest condensed books
and Louis L'Amour.
Look magazine.
Erle Stanley Gardners.
Every evening I load up the cart and make my rounds.
I enter the names on this clipboard here.
Easy, peasy, Japanese y.
Any questions
How long have you been librarian
I come here in '05, and they made me librarian in 1912.
And have you ever had an assistant
No
Not much to it, really.
Why me
Why now
I don't know.
But it'd be nice to have some company down here.
That's him
That's the one.
I'm Dekins.
I was
thinking about setting up some kind of trust fund for my kids' educations.
I see.
Why don't we have a seat and talk it over.
Do you have a piece of paper and a pencil
Thanks.
So
Ms Dekins..
And then Andy says, Ms Dekins
do you want your sons to go to Harvard or Yale
He didn't say that
As God as my witness
Dekins blinked for a second
then he laughed and actually shook Andy's hand.
My ass
Shook his hand.
I tell you, I near soiled myself
All he needed was a suit and tie and a jiggly hula gal on his desk
he'd have been Ms Dufresne, if you please.
Making a few friends
I wouldn't say friends.
I'm a convicted murderer who provides sound financial planning.
It's a wonderful pet to have.
Got you out of the laundry, though.
It might do more than that.
How about expanding the library
Get some new books.
If you ask for something, ask for a pool table.
How do you expect to do that
I mean..
get new books in here, Ms Dufresne, if you please.
I'll ask the warden for funds.
Six wardens have been through here in my tenure, and I've learned..
one immutable, universal truth:
Not one of them born whose asshole
wouldn't pucker up tighter than a snare drum when you ask for funds.
The budget's stretched thin as it is
I see.
Perhaps I could write the state senate and request funds from them
They have only three ways to spend the taxpayers' money for prisons:
More walls, more bars, more guards.
I'd like to try, with permission
A letter a week.
They can't ignore me forever
Sure can.
But you write your letters if it makes you happy.
I'll even mail them for you
How's that
So Andy started writing a letter a week
just like he said.
And, just like Norton said
Andy got no answers.
The following April, Andy did tax returns for half the guards at Shawshank.
Year after that, he did them all
including the warden's.
Year after that, they rescheduled the intramural season
to coincide with tax season.
The guards on the opposing teams all remembered to bring their W 2s.
So Moresby Prison
issued you a gun, but you paid for it.
Right
The holster too.
That's tax deductible
You can write that off.
Yes, sir
Andy was a regular cottage industry.
In fact, it got so busy at tax time, he was allowed a staff.
Could you hand me a stack of 1040s
Got me out of the wood shop a month out of the year, and that was fine by me.
And still, he kept sending those letters.
It's Brooks.
Watch the door.
Please, Brooks.
Calm the fuck down
Stay back
Stay back, goddamn it
What's going on
One second he's fine, then out come the knife.
We can talk about this, right
There's nothing to talk about
I'll cut his fucking throat.
What's he done to you
It's what they done
I got no choice.
You won't hurt Heywood
We all know that.
Right, Heywood
Sure
I know that.
He's a friend of yours, and Brooks is a reasonable man.
Right, guys
So put the knife down
Brooks, look at me.
Put the knife down.
Look at his neck, for God's sake.
Look at his neck
He's bleeding.
It's the only
It's the only way they'd let me stay.
This is crazy
You don't want to do this.
Put it..
Put it down.
Take it easy.
You'll be all right.
Him
What about me
Crazy old fool damn near cut my throat
You've had worse from shaving.
What did you do to set him off
Nothing
I come in here to say farewell.
Ain't you heard
His parole's come through.
I just don't understand what happened in there, that's all.
Old man's crazy as a rat in a tin shithouse.
That's enough out of you.
Heard he had you shitting your pants
Fuck you.
Knock it off.
Brooks ain't no bug.
He's just institutionalized.
Institutionalized, my ass.
The man's been in here 50 years, Heywood, 50 years
This is all he knows.
In here, he's an important man
an educated man.
Outside, he's nothing.
Just a used up con with arthritis in both hands.
Probably couldn't get a library card if he tried.
You know what I'm trying to say
I do believe you're talking out of your ass.
You believe whatever you want.
But I tell you these walls are funny.
First you hate them.
Then you get used to them.
Enough time passes
you get so you depend on them
That's institutionalized.
Shit.
I could never get like that
Oh, yeah
Wait till you've been here as long as Brooks.
Goddamn right.
They send you here for life
that's exactly what they take.
Part that counts, anyway.
I can't take care of you no more, Jake.
You go on now.
You're free.
Good luck, Brooksie.
Take care of yourself, Brooks
Dear fellas:
I can't believe how fast things move on the outside.
Watch it, old timer
Want to get killed
I saw an automobile once when I was a kid
but now they're everywhere.
The world went and got itself in a big damn hurry.
The parole board got me into this halfway house
called The Brewer..
and a job
bagging groceries at the Food Way.
It's hard work and I try to keep up
but my hands hurt most of the time.
Make sure your man double bags.
Last time, the bottom near came out.
Make sure you double bag like the lady says
Understand
Yes, sir
Surely will.
I don't think the store manager likes me very much.
Sometimes after work, I go to the park and feed the birds.
I keep thinking
Jake might just show up and say hello.
But he never does.
I hope, wherever he is, he's doing okay and making new friends.
I have trouble sleeping at night.
I have bad dreams, like I'm falling.
I wake up scared.
Sometimes it takes me a while to remember where I am.
Maybe I should get me a gun and rob the Food Way so they'd send me home.
I could shoot the manager while I was at it
Sort of like a bonus.
I guess I'm too old for that sort of nonsense anymore.
I don't like it here.
I'm tired of being afraid all the time
I've decided
not to stay.
I doubt they'll kick up any fuss
not for an old crook like me
I doubt they'll kick up any fuss, not for an old crook like me.
P.S
Tell Heywood I'm sorry I put a knife to his throat
No hard feelings
Brooks.
He should have died in here.
What the fuck have you done
It's a goddamn mess, I'll tell you that.
What's all this
You tell me
They're addressed to you.
Take it
Dear Ms Dufresne:
In response to your repeated inquiries..
the state has allocated the enclosed funds for your library project.
This is $200
In addition, the library district has generously responded
with a donation of used books and sundries.
We trust this will fill your needs
We now consider the matter closed
Please stop sending us letters.
Clear all this out before the warden gets back.
Yes, sir.
Good for you, Andy.
It only took six years.
From now on, I'll write two letters a week instead of one.
I believe you're crazy enough
Get this stuff out
like he said
I've got to pinch a loaf.
When I come back
this is all gone, all right
Do you hear that
Dufresne
Andy, let me out
I have no idea to this day what those two Italian ladies were singing about.
Truth is, I don't want to know.
Some things are best left unsaid.
I like to think it was something so beautiful
it can't be expressed in words
and makes your heart ache because of it.
I tell you, those voices soared
higher and farther than anybody in a gray place dares to dream.
It was like a beautiful bird flapped into our drab cage
and made those walls dissolve away.
And for the briefest of moments
every last man at Shawshank felt free.
It pissed the warden off something awful.
Open the door.
Open it up
Dufresne, open this door
Turn that off
I am warning you
You're mine now.
Andy got two weeks in the hole for that little stunt.
On your feet.
Hey, look who's here
Maestro
You couldn't play something good, huh
Like Hank Williams
They broke the door down before I could take requests.
Was it worth two weeks
Easiest time I ever did.
No such thing as easy time in the hole
A week in the hole is like a year.
Damn straight
I had Ms Mozart to keep me company.
So they let you tote that record player down there, huh
It was in here.
In here.
That's the beauty of music
They
can't get that from you.
Haven't you ever felt that way about music
Well, I played a mean harmonica as a younger man.
Lost interest in it, though.
Didn't make much sense in here.
Here's where it makes the most sense.
You need it so you don't forget.
Forget
Forget that there are..
places
in the world that aren't made out of stone.
There's something
inside
that they can't get to
that they can't touch.
That's yours.
What are you talking about
Hope.
Let me tell you something, my friend.
Hope is a dangerous thing.
Hope can drive a man insane.
It's got no use on the inside.
You'd better get used to that idea.
Like Brooks did
Sit down.
Says here that you've served 30 years of a life sentence.
You feel you've been rehabilitated
Oh, yes, sir.
Without a doubt.
I can honestly say I'm a changed man.
No danger to society here.
God's honest truth.
Absolutely rehabilitated.
Thirty years.
Jesus, when you say it like that
You wonder where it went.
I wonder where 10 years went.
Here.
A little parole rejection present.
Go ahead and open it.
Went through one of your competitors.
I hope you don't mind
I wanted it to be a surprise.
It's very pretty.
Thank you.
You going to play it
No.
Not right now.
Roll in
Lights out
Andy was as good as his word.
He wrote two letters a week instead of one.
In 1959, the state senate finally clued in to the fact
they couldn't buy him off with just a $200 check.
Appropriations Committee voted an annual payment of $500
just to shut him up.
And you'd be amazed how far Andy could stretch it.
He made deals with book clubs, charity groups.
He bought remaindered books by the pound
Treasure Island.
Robert Louis..
Stevenson.
Fiction, adventure.
What's next
I got here Auto Repair
and Soap Carving.
Trade skills and hobbies
Under Educational, behind you.
Count of Monte Crisco.
That's Cristo, you dumb shit.
By Alexandree
Dum ass.
Dumb ass.
Dumb ass
Dumas
Know what that's about
You'd like it
It's about a prison break.
We ought to file that under Educational too, oughtn't we
The rest of us did our best to pitch in when and where we could.
By the year Kennedy was shot
Andy had transformed a storage room smelling of turpentine
into the best prison library in New England
complete with a fine selection of Hank Williams.
That was also when Warden Norton
instituted his famous Inside Out program.
You may remember reading about it.
It made the papers and got his picture in Look magazine.
It's no free ride
but rather a genuine progressive advance
in corrections and rehabilitation.
Our inmates, properly supervised
will be put to work outside these walls
performing all manner of public service.
These men can learn the value of an honest day's labor
while providing a valuable service to the community
and at a bare minimum of expense to Ms and Mrs John Q
Taxpayer.
Of course he didn't tell the press
that bare minimum of expense is a fairly loose term.
There are 100 different ways to skim off the top.
Men, materials, you name it.
And oh, my Lord, how the money rolled in
At this rate, you'll put me out of business.
With this pool of slave labor, you can underbid any contractor in town.
We're providing a valuable community service.
That's fine for the papers, but I've got a family to feed.
We go back a long way.
I need this highway contract
I don't get it and I go under
That's a fact.
You have some of this fine pie
my missus made for you
You think about that.
I wouldn't worry too much about this contract.
It seems to me I already got my boys committed elsewhere.
You be sure and thank Maisie for this fine pie.
And behind every shady deal
behind every dollar earned
there was Andy, keeping the books.
Two deposits.
Maine National and New England First
Night drops as always, sir.
Get my stuff to the laundry
Two suits for dry clean and a bag of whatnot.
If they over starch my shirts again, they'll hear from me.
How do I look
Very nice
Big charity to do up Portland way.
Governor will be there.
You want the rest of this
Woman can't bake worth shit.
Thank you, sir.
He's got his fingers in a lot of pies, from what I hear.
He's got scams you haven't even dreamed of
Kickbacks on his kickbacks.
A river of dirty money running through here.
Sooner or later, he'll have to explain where it came from.
That's where I come in.
I channel it
Filter it
Funnel it.
Stocks, securities, tax free municipals.
I send it out into the real world, and when it comes back
Clean as a virgin's honeypot, huh
Cleaner.
By the time Norton retires, I'll have made him a millionaire.
If they ever catch on, he'll wind up in here wearing a number himself.
I thought you had more faith in me than that.
I know you're good, but all that paper leaves a trail.
Now anybody gets curious
FBI, IRS, whatever.
It'll lead to somebody.
Sure it is, but not to me, and certainly not to the warden.
All right, who
Randall Stevens.
Who
The silent silent partner.
He's the guilty one, the man with the bank accounts.
It's where the filtering process starts.
They trace anything, it'll just lead to him.
But who is he
He's a phantom, an apparition
Second cousin to Harvey the Rabbit.
I conjured him..
out of thin air.
He doesn't exist, except on paper.
You can't just make a person up.
Sure you can, if you know how the system works.
It's amazing what you can accomplish by mail.
Ms Stevens has a birth certificate
driver's license, Social Security.
You're shitting me.
If they trace any accounts, they'll wind up chasing
a figment of my imagination.
Well, I'll be damned
Did I say you were good
Shit, you are Rembrandt.
The funny thing is
on the outside, I was an honest man, straight as an arrow.
I had to come to prison to be a crook.
Ever bother you
I don't run the scams
I just process the profits.
A fine line, maybe
but I also built that library
and used it to help guys get their high school diploma.
Why do you think he lets me do all that
Keep you happy and doing the laundry.
Money instead of sheets.
Well, I work cheap
That's the tradeoff.
Tommy Williams came to Shawshank in 1965
on a two year stretch for B and E.
That's breaking and entering to you.
Cops caught him sneaking TV sets out the back door of a JC Penney.
Young punk.
Ms Rock 'n' Roll..
cocky as hell.
Come on, old boys
Moving like molasses
Making me look bad.
We liked him immediately.
I'm backing out the door and I got the TV like this.
A big old thing
I couldn't see shit
Then I hear this voice
Freeze, kid, hands in the air. I was standing there, holding onto that TV
Finally the voice says:
You hear what I said, boy
I say, Yes, sir
I did
But if I drop this, you get me on destruction of property too.
You done some stretch in Cashman, right
Yeah, that was an easy piece of time, let me tell you.
Weekend furloughs
Work programs.
Not like here.
Sounds like you done time all over.
I've been in and out since I was 13.
Name it, chances are I've been there.
Perhaps you should try a new profession.
What I mean is
you're not a very good thief
You should try something else.
Yeah, what the hell you know about it, Capone
What are you in for
Me
A lawyer fucked me.
Everybody's innocent in here
Don't you know that
As it turned out, Tommy had himself a young wife and a new baby girl.
Maybe he thought of them on the streets
or his child growing up not knowing her daddy.
Whatever it was
something lit a fire under that boy's ass.
Thought I might try for my high school equivalency.
Hear you helped a couple of fellas with that.
I don't waste time with losers, Tommy.
I ain't no goddamn loser.
You mean that
Yeah.
You really mean that
Yes, sir, I do.
Good
Because if we do this
we do it all the way, a hundred percent, nothing half assed.
Thing is, see
I don't read so good
Well.
You don't read
so well.
We'll get to that.
So Andy took Tommy under his wing.
Started walking him through his ABC's.
Tommy took to it pretty well too.
Boy found brains he never knew he had.
Before long, Andy started him on his course requirements.
He really liked the kid.
Gave him a thrill to help a youngster crawl off the shit heap.
But that wasn't the only reason.
Prison time is slow time.
So you do what you can to keep going.
Some fellas collect stamps.
Others build matchstick houses.
Andy built a library.
Now he needed a new project.
Tommy was it.
It was the same reason he spent years shaping and polishing those rocks.
The same reason he hung his fantasy girlies on the wall.
In prison
a man will do most anything to keep his mind occupied.
By 1966, right about the time Tommy was getting ready to take his exams
it was lovely Raquel.
Time.
Well
Well, it's for shit.
I wasted a whole year of my time with this bullshit.
It's probably not that bad.
I didn't get a thing right
It might as well have been in Chinese.
Let's see how the score comes out.
I'll tell you how the goddamn score comes out.
Two points, right there
There's your goddamn score
Goddamn cats crawling up trees, 5 times 5 is 25
Fuck this place
Fuck it
I feel bad.
I let him down.
That's crap, kid.
He's proud of you.
We're old friends, I know him as good as anybody.
Smart fellow, ain't he
Smart as they come
He was a banker on the outside.
What's he in here for anyway
Murder.
The hell, you say.
You wouldn't think it to look at the guy.
Caught his wife in bed with some golf pro
Greased them both.
What
About four years ago
I was in Thomaston on a two to three stretch.
I stole a car.
It was a dumb fuck thing to do.
About six months left to go
I get a new cellmate in.
Elmo Blatch.
Big, twitchy fucker.
Kind of roomie you pray you don't get
You know what I'm saying
Six to twelve, armed burglary.
Said he pulled hundreds ofjobs.
Hard to believe, high strung as he was
You cut a loud fart, he jumped three feet.
Talked all the time too
That's the other thing
He never shut up.
Places he'd been in
jobs he'd pulled, women he fucked.
Even people he killed
People who gave him shit.
That's how he put it.
So one night, like a joke..
I say to him, Elmo, who did you kill
So he says:
I got me this job one time, busing tables at a country club
so I could case all these big rich pricks that come in.
So I pick out this guy
go in one night..
and do his place.
He wakes up
and gives me shit.
So I killed him.
Him and this tasty bitch he was with.
And that's the best part.
She's fucking this prick, see
this golf pro, but she's married to some other guy.
Some hotshot banker.
And he's the one they pinned it on.
I have to say that's the most amazing story I ever heard.
What amazes me most is you'd be taken in by it.
Sir
It's obvious this fellow Williams is impressed with you.
He hears your tale of woe and naturally wants to cheer you up.
He's young, not terribly bright.
It's not surprising he wouldn't know what a state he put you in.
Sir, he's telling the truth.
Let's say for the moment this Blatch does exist
You think he'd just fall to his knees and cry, Yes, I did it
I confess. By the way, add a life term to my sentence.
With Tommy's testimony, I can get a new trial.
That's assuming Blatch is still there.
Chances are, he'd be released by now.
They'd have his last known address, names of relatives
It's a chance, isn't it
How can you be so obtuse
What
What did you call me
Obtuse
Is it deliberate
You're forgetting yourself.
The country club will have his old timecards.
Records, W 2s with his name on them.
If you want to indulge this fantasy, it's your business.
Don't make it mine
This meeting is over.
If I got out, I'd never mention what happens here.
I'd be as indictable as you for laundering that money.
Don't ever mention money to me again, you sorry son of a bitch
Not in this office
not anywhere
Get in here, now
I just wanted to put you at ease, that's all.
Solitary
A month
Yes, sir.
What's the matter with you
Get him out of here.
This is my chance to get out
It's my life
Don't you understand
Get him out
A month in the hole.
That's the longest stretch I ever heard of.
It's all my fault.
Bullshit.
You didn't pull the trigger or convict him.
Are you saying Andy is innocent
I mean, for real innocent
It looks that way.
Sweet Jesus.
How long has he been here now
What is that
Nineteen years.
Williams, Thomas
Yeah, over here.
What you got
Board of Education.
That son of a bitch mailed it.
You going to open it or stand there with your thumb up your butt
Thumb up my butt sounds better.
Skeets, come on
Give me that, you shithead.
Floyd, come on.
Will you throw that away, please
Well, shit.
The kid passed
C plus average.
Thought you'd like to know.
Warden wants to talk.
Out here
That's what the man said.
Warden
I'm asking you to keep this conversation just between us.
I feel awkward enough as it is.
We got a situation here.
I think you can appreciate that.
Yes, sir.
I sure can.
I tell you, son, this thing really came along and knocked my wind out.
It's got me up nights
That's the truth.
The right thing to do
sometimes it's hard to know what that is.
Do you understand
I need your help, son.
If I'm going to move on this
there can't be the least little shred of doubt.
I have to know
if what you told Dufresne was the truth.
Yes, sir.
Absolutely.
Would you be willing to swear before a judge and jury
with your hand on the Good Book
and take an oath before Almighty God himself
Just give me that chance.
That's what I thought.
I'm sure by now you've heard.
Terrible thing.
A man that young
less than a year to go, trying to escape.
Broke Captain Hadley's heart to shoot him.
Truly, it did.
We just have to put it behind us.
Move on.
I'm done.
Everything stops.
Get someone else to run your scams.
Nothing stops.
Nothing.
Or you will do the hardest time there is.
No more protection from the guards.
I'll pull you out of that 1  bunk Hilton and cast you down with the sodomites.
You'll think you've been fucked by a train.
And the library
Gone.
Sealed off, brick by brick.
We'll have us a little book barbecue in the yard.
They'll see the flames for miles.
We'll dance around it like wild lnjuns.
You understand me
Catching my drift
Or am I being obtuse
Give him another month to think about it.
My wife used to say I'm a hard man to know.
Like a closed book.
Complained about it all the time.
She was beautiful.
God, I loved her.
I didn't know how to show it, that's all.
I killed her, Red.
I didn't pull the trigger
but I drove her away.
That's why she died, because of me
the way I am.
That don't make you a murderer.
Bad husband, maybe.
Feel bad about it if you want, but you didn't pull the trigger.
No, I didn't.
Somebody else did.
And I wound up in here.
Bad luck, I guess.
It floats around.
It's got to land on somebody.
It was my turn, that's all.
I was in the path of the tornado.
I just didn't expect the storm would last as long as it has.
Think you'll ever get out of here
Me
Yeah.
One day, when I got a long, white beard
and two or three marbles rolling around upstairs, they'll let me out.
I tell you where I'd go.
Zihuatanejo.
Say what
It's in Mexico.
A little place on the Pacific Ocean.
You know what the Mexicans say about the Pacific
They say it has no memory.
That's where I want to live the rest of my life.
A warm place with no memory.
Open up a little hotel
right on the beach.
Buy some worthless old boat
and fix it up new.
Take my guests out
charter fishing.
Zihuatanejo.
In a place like that, I could use a man that knows how to get things.
I don't think I could make it on the outside.
I been in here most of my life.
I'm an institutional man now.
Just like Brooks was.
You underestimate yourself.
I don't think so.
In here I'm the guy who can get things for you, sure, but
outside all you need is the Yellow Pages.
Hell, I wouldn't know where to begin.
Pacific Ocean
Shit.
Scare me to death, something that big.
Not me.
I didn't shoot my wife, and I didn't shoot her lover.
Whatever mistakes I made, I've paid for them and then some.
That hotel, that boat
I don't think that's too much to ask.
You shouldn't be doing this to yourself.
This is just shitty pipe dreams.
Mexico is way down there and you're in here
and that's the way it is.
Yeah, right
That's the way it is.
It's down there and I'm in here.
I guess it comes down to a simple choice.
Get busy living
or get busy dying.
If you ever get out of here, do me a favor.
Sure, Andy
Anything.
There's a big hayfield up near Buxton
You know where Buxton is
A lot of hayfields up there
One in particular.
It's got a long rock wall with a big oak tree at the north end.
It's like something out of a Robert Frost poem.
It's where I asked my wife to marry me.
We went there for a picnic
and made love under that oak
and I asked and she said yes.
Promise me, Red.
If you ever get out..
find that spot.
At the base of that wall, there's a rock that has no earthly business in Maine.
Piece of black, volcanic glass.
Something's buried under it I want you to have.
What, Andy
What's buried under there
You'll have to pry it up..
to see.
No, I'm telling you
The guy is
He's talking funny.
I'm really worried about him.
Let's keep an eye on him.
That's fine during the day, but at night he's all alone.
Oh, Lord.
What
Andy come down to the loading dock today.
He asked me for a length of rope.
Rope
Six feet long.
And you gave it to him.
Sure
Why wouldn't I
Jesus
Heywood.
How was I supposed to know
Remember Brooks Hatlen
Andy would never do that.
Never.
I don't know.
Every man has his breaking point.
Lickety split
Want to get home.
Just about finished, sir.
Three deposits tonight.
Get my stuff down to the laundry.
And shine my shoes.
I want them looking like mirrors
Yes, sir.
It's good having you back.
Place wasn't the same without you.
Lights out
I've had some long nights in the stir.
Alone in the dark with nothing but your thoughts
time can draw out like a blade.
That was the longest night of my life.
Give me a count
Tier 3 south, clear
Man missing on tier 2, cell 245
Dufresne
Come out
You're holding up the show
Don't make me come down or I'll thump your skull for you
Damn it, you're putting me behind
I got a schedule to keep.
You'd better be sick or dead in there
I shit you not
You hear me
Oh, my Holy God.
I want every man on this cellblock questioned.
Start with that friend of his
Who
Him.
Open 237.
What do you mean, He just wasn't here
Don't say that to me.
Don't say that to me again
But, sir, he wasn't.
I can see that, Haig
Think I'm blind
Is that what you're saying
Am I blind, Haig
No, sir
What about you
You blind
Tell me what this is
Last night's count.
You see Dufresne's name there
I sure do
Right there
Dufresne.
He was in his cell at lights out.
Stands to reason he'd still be here in the morning.
I want him found.
Not tomorrow, not after breakfast
Now
Yes, sir.
Let's go
Move your butts
Move it
Stand.
Well
Well, what
I see you two all the time
You're thick as thieves, you are.
He must have said something.
No, sir, warden
Not a word.
Lord, it's a miracle
Man vanished like a fart in the wind.
Nothing left
but some damn rocks on a windowsill.
And that cupcake on the wall
Let's ask her.
Maybe she knows.
What say there, fuzzy britches
Feel like talking
Guess not.
Why should she be any different
This is a conspiracy.
That's what this is.
One big, damn conspiracy
And everyone's in on it
Including her
In 1966..
Andy Dufresne escaped
from Shawshank Prison.
All they found was a muddy set of prison clothes
a bar of soap..
and an old rock hammer
damn near worn down to the nub.
I remember thinking it would take a man 600 years to tunnel through the wall with it.
Old Andy did it in less than 20.
Oh, Andy loved geology.
I imagine it appealed to his meticulous nature.
An ice age here
million years of mountain building there.
Geology is the study of pressure and time.
That's all it takes, really.
Pressure
and time.
That and a big goddamn poster.
Like I said
in prison, a man will do anything to keep his mind occupied.
Seems Andy's favorite hobby was toting his wall out into the exercise yard
a handful at a time.
I guess after Tommy was killed
Andy decided he'd been here long enough.
Lickety split
I want to get home.
I'm just about finished, sir.
Three deposits tonight.
Andy did like he was told.
Buffed those shoes to a high mirror shine.
The guards simply didn't notice.
Neither did I.
I mean, seriously
how often do you really look at a man's shoes
Andy crawled to freedom through 500 yards
of shit smelling foulness I can't even imagine.
Or maybe I just don't want to.
Five hundred yards.
That's the length of five football fields.
Just shy of half a mile.
The next morning, right about the time Raquel was spilling her secret
a man nobody ever laid eyes on before
strolled into the Maine National Bank.
Until that moment, he didn't exist.
Except on paper
May I help you
He had all the proper ID
Driver's license, birth certificate, Social Security card.
And the signature was a spot on match.
I must say I'm sorry to be losing your business.
I hope you'll enjoy living abroad.
Thank you.
I'm sure I will.
Here's your cashier's check, sir
Will there be anything else
Please.
Would you add this to your outgoing mail
I'd be happy to.
Good day, sir.
Ms Stevens visited nearly a dozen banks in the Portland area that morning.
All told, he blew town
with better than $370,000 of Warden Norton's money.
Severance pay for 19 years.
Good morning, Portland Daily Bugle.
Byron Hadley
You have the right to remain silent.
If you give up this right, anything you say can be held against you in court.
I wasn't there to see it, but I hear Byron Hadley sobbed like a girl
when they took him away.
Norton had no intention of going that quietly.
Samuel Norton.
We have a warrant for your arrest
Open up.
Open the door.
I'm not sure which key.
Make it easy on yourself, Norton
I like to think the last thing that went through his head
other than that bullet
was to wonder how the hell Andy Dufresne ever got the best of him.
Not long after the warden deprived us of his company
I got a postcard in the mail.
It was blank, but the postmark said
Fort Hancock, Texas.
Fort Hancock
right on the border.
That's where Andy crossed.
When I picture him heading south in his own car with the top down
it always makes me laugh.
Andy Dufresne
who crawled through a river of shit
and came out clean on the other side.
Andy Dufresne
headed for the Pacific.
Hadley's got him by the throat, right
He says, I believe this boy's about to have himself an accident.
Those of us who knew him best talk about him often.
I swear, the stuff he pulled..
My friends could use a couple of beers.
And he got it
Sometimes it makes me sad, though
Andy being gone.
I have to remind myself that some birds aren't meant to be caged.
Their feathers are just too bright.
And when they fly away
the part of you that knows it was a sin to lock them up does rejoice.
But still
the place you live in is that much more drab and empty that they're gone.
I guess I just miss my friend.
Please sit down.
Ellis Boyd Redding
your files say you've served 40 years of a life sentence.
You feel you've been rehabilitated
Rehabilitated
Well, now, let me see.
I don't have any idea what that means.
It means you're ready to rejoin society
I know what you think it means, sonny.
To me it's just a made up word.
A politician's word so that
young fellas like yourself can wear a suit and a tie
and have a job.
What do you really want to know
Am I sorry for what I did
Well, are you
There's not a day goes by I don't feel regret.
Not because I'm in here or because you think I should.
I look back on the way I was then
a young
stupid kid who committed that terrible crime.
I want to talk to him.
I want to try and talk some sense to him.
Tell him the way things are.
But I can't.
That kid's long gone
and this old man is all that's left.
I got to live with that.
Rehabilitated
It's just a bullshit word.
So you go on and stamp your forms, sonny, and stop wasting my time.
Because to tell you the truth
I don't give a shit.
Here you go, miss.
Restroom break
You don't need to ask me every time you need to go take a piss
Just go.
Yes, sir.
Forty years I've been asking permission to piss.
I can't squeeze a drop without say so.
There's a harsh truth to face.
No way I'm going to make it on the outside.
All I do anymore is think of ways to break my parole
so maybe they'd send me back.
Terrible thing, to live in fear.
Brooks Hatlen knew it.
Knew it all too well.
All I want is to be back where things make sense.
Where I won't have to be afraid all the time.
Only one thing stops me.
A promise I made to Andy.
There it is.
Much obliged, sir
Dear Red:
If you're reading this, you've gotten out
and if you've come this far, maybe you're willing to come a bit further.
You remember the name of the town, don't you
Zihuatanejo.
I could use a good man to help me get my project on wheels.
I'll keep an eye out for you, and the chessboard ready.
Remember, Red
hope is a good thing
maybe the best of things.
And no good thing ever dies.
I will be hoping that this letter finds you
and finds you well.
Your friend..
Andy
Get busy living..
or get busy dying.
That's goddamn right.
For the second time in my life
I'm guilty of committing a crime.
Parole violation.
Of course, I doubt they'll toss up any roadblocks for that.
Not for an old crook like me.
Fort Hancock, Texas, please.
I find I'm so excited I can barely sit still or hold a thought in my head.
I think it's the excitement only a free man can feel.
A free man at the start of a long journey
whose conclusion is uncertain.
I hope I can make it across the border.
I hope to see my friend and shake his hand.
I hope the Pacific is as blue as it has been in my dreams.
I hope.